<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://deeglaze.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://deeglaze.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-08-20T04:02:45+00:00</updated><id>https://deeglaze.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal homepage for computer scientist and software engineer Dionna Glaze, Ph.D. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Mentoring A Swe Part0</title><link href="https://deeglaze.github.io/blog/2024/Mentoring-a-SWE-part0/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mentoring A Swe Part0"/><published>2024-07-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://deeglaze.github.io/blog/2024/Mentoring-a-SWE-part0</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://deeglaze.github.io/blog/2024/Mentoring-a-SWE-part0/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="mentoring-a-software-engineer-part-0">Mentoring a Software Engineer: Part 0</h1> <p>This is a series of posts I want to start as a way of thinking through how I approach mentoring. This may not follow the narrative structure of a journal, but they are notes to myself. I am not writing this as instructional material, but if you find value in it, do let me know.</p> <h2 id="goals">Goals</h2> <p>I find a mentor/mentee relationship to be effective when it is goal-oriented and time-bounded. When I mentor someone in a professional context, I have three goals, and they’re all about helping a mentee with their goals.</p> <p>Goal 1. Establish context. A mentee should be seeking a mentor to reach a goal. Am I a good fit to help them reach it?</p> <p>Goal 2. determine the areas that need growth in order to reach the goal. Why do they need help reaching their goal?</p> <p>Goal 3. nurture that growth with suggestions, encouragement, and check-ins.</p> <p>I have the explicit non-goal of presenting a rose-tinted view of myself from the mentee’s point of view. I don’t need to feed my ego with someone that looks up to me. I need my mentee to see that flaws and limitations are everpresent in the human experience, but we can still manage to improve upon ourselves.</p> <h2 id="goal-1-establish-context">Goal 1: establish context</h2> <p>Maybe someone wants help formulating <em>more specific</em> goals on their way to their main goal, say, a promotion. This is what I typically have people coming to me for. At Google there are plenty of resources about this. I need folks to dig a little deeper for a more intrinsic career goal.</p> <p>What I find to be fascinating to watch is how unprepared a person is when asked, “would you be happy in that role?” Certainly more money is motivator. The stress of working a role with more responsibilities that you can’t handle may tip the scales away from the cash bump.</p> <p>I need to determine someone’s motivations in order to effectively guide them. As a mentor, there’s no point in my suggesting someone do something they’re entirely unmotivated to do since they likely won’t do it. They won’t try and they won’t improve.</p> <p>Are these person’s motivations even scrutible to me? If so, I might be able to take them on as a mentee.</p> <h2 id="goal-2-identify-growth-areas">Goal 2: identify growth areas</h2> <p>This can take a fair amount of the mentorship time. I need to get to know someone and their concrete struggles to determine where they need help. A meeting with a mentee is typically only 30 minutes, so it’s important to try to drive the conversation away from being just a gripe session.</p> <p>Is this person an arrogant “misunderstood genius”? Is this person too hesitant about their own ideas to try to advance them? Is this person stuck in a rut and looking for a way out of a common grind?</p> <p>I can only do so much with our limited time together that I try to pick out just a couple aspects to work on, with concrete goals attached. If a mentee and I can agree on what to prioritize to work on, then we can get to work.</p> <h2 id="goal-3-nurture-growth">Goal 3: nurture growth</h2> <p>I will try to have my mentee internalize the three Hs:</p> <ul> <li>Be Humble.</li> <li>Be Helpful.</li> <li>Be Hungry.</li> </ul> <p>I find that staying humble will improve your relationships with people. People are generally more willing to hear you out when they like you.</p> <p>To be more than likeable, I think you need to contribute something more than comic relief–to be helpful. Being helpful doesn’t just mean picking up an on-call shift for someone going on vacation. Helpfulness can extend to all areas of the team and the business, depending on how you structure your help.</p> <p>If you’re “fat and happy”, you have little motivation to improve. Therefore, I find that keeping momentum in self improvement requires carrying an intrinsic amount of hunger to have a greater impact.</p> <h2 id="closing-time">Closing time</h2> <p>I plan to go into more detail about how I go about achieving my goals as a mentor in later posts. Next, I want to detail some goals folks have had (abstractly) and how I went about or would go about getting more information about them.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Mentoring a Software Engineer: Part 0]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blogging again</title><link href="https://deeglaze.github.io/blog/2024/blogging-again/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blogging again"/><published>2024-05-25T21:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-25T21:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://deeglaze.github.io/blog/2024/blogging-again</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://deeglaze.github.io/blog/2024/blogging-again/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve had a few blogs in my lifetime. College. Grad school. First time parent. Pretty much every one of them had math in them. Yes, even when writing to my infant in some hypothetical future when they could understand me. Now I’m starting back up with my “professional” slice of life, but still with a fair amount of philosophizing and experimental thinking. I just want to tell stories again in a longer form and in a manner I feel more ownership of.</p> <p>I need this post to be more than, ¨more soon!¨, so I’ll talk about why I feel the need to own this content more than what I post on social media. Ownership is the topic of this post. OooOooh, so adult. Don’t worry, I’m still financially illiterate intentionally because I ethically disagree with gaming the system of capital to enrich myself without adding any social good. Could I then turn around and reinvest any capital gains back into community? Yes, but that thinking is how we get to the system we have today, where communities that are systematically disenfranchised by the owning class are expected to tell sob stories for pity money that is a tiny fraction of what tax-based governmental support could otherwise provide. This is where I have to follow up with and also explain I’m not a monster and still do donate my money and time to community. Yes, that. The sob story comment comes from the frustated stories of a friend that is a former executive director for a reasonably large 501c(3) that provides services to victims of gender-based violence. This whole explanation is condemned by fascists as virtue signalling, and of course the truth is in neither extreme. I’ll probably have a post later about my understanding of “truth” but not in this post.</p> <p>Popping the stack to get back from the meta-post to the post. I currently work for Google, one of the powerhouses behind “free” web-based products, and this is of course a topic of consternation for me. As a broke student, free was good enough. I didn’t care much about longevity, just access. Getting the invite to the gmail beta was amazing. Getting the invite to “the facebook” was amazing. I did still worry about longetivy while signing a license agreement that I own nothing of what I just paid for. I still signed it. There aren’t a whole lot of people with enough privilege to reject the license agreements and still maintain their ability to carry on with life normally.</p> <p>I could go on about the inequities about access to art and history more generally, but honestly I just wanted to be able to share the things I loved with my child when they grew to an age where they could appreciate it. Children grow up in their own cultural context though. I didn’t care about my parents’ love for certain types of music and art. I complained during the museum trips. I have the math books that inspired me. The video games that defined me. The movies that shape how I process social situations with direct quotes as a means of forming a shared understanding. I’ve tried to share what I love, but I don’t have particularly inspiring energy, or a pedagogical skillset that could help convey why I love certain things. My kid gets to be their own person and reject anything I try to share as a means of connecting about something we could both love. I still do get upset at the thought that I couldn’t even have that chance to share a culturally meaningful artifact due to some servers shutting down or the legal nightmare emulator authoring can be to preserve old technologies. I’m not sure how dire it is though, of all things. I’m glad there are people that fight all the wall-building.</p> <p>In terms of owning my own words, I’m just at a point where I’m more comfortable writing human-readable text files I can easily port to other publication methods. I don’t have my twitter posts backed up. They don’t maintain the context of the conversations I was having. They’re not particularly great at conveying a complete thought that could be revisited years later the way articles can. The fall of Twitter is not as much of a blow to me as it has been to other communities, but mostly because I’ve been rather insular since the start. Folks I wanted to maintain a connection to also had the opportunity to experiment with Mastodon before the truly unhinged days arrived. Still, even with my participation in the Fediverse on an instance I financially contribute to, the medium is different from here, where “the feed” is all me, and longer.</p> <p>These words are published with no license. They are all under my copyright. I do not consent to their use in any algorithmic training dataset.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="update"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve had a few blogs in my lifetime. College. Grad school. First time parent. Pretty much every one of them had math in them. Yes, even when writing to my infant in some hypothetical future when they could understand me. Now I’m starting back up with my “professional” slice of life, but still with a fair amount of philosophizing and experimental thinking. I just want to tell stories again in a longer form and in a manner I feel more ownership of.]]></summary></entry></feed>